Finding Aid for Senior Society (University of Michigan) records, 1916-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Senior Society (University of Michigan) records 1916-1968 1940-1960
Senior Society (University of Michigan).
1 linear foot
2009142 Bimu F41 2
Women's honorary society for unaffiliated women students at the University of Michigan established in 1905, one of several Women's honorary societies, including Scroll and Wyvern. Records include minutes, 1916-1927 and 1951-1962, scrapbooks, 1941-1954, 1965-1968, and miscellaneous records and membership information. Scrapbooks include clippings, wartime women's activities during World War II, invitations, membership, and photographs of "tapping" and initiation. Records of Scroll and Wyvern are included in the scrapbooks as is the Assembly Association.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was acquired in June 2009 (donor no. 10222 ).
No further additions to the records expected.
The Senior Society records are open for research without restriction.
The Senior Society formed as an honor society based on scholastic achievement and leadership for independent (non-sorority) senior class women in 1905, the same year as the senior women's honorary Mortar Board. The group came together under the guidance of then Dean of Women Myra P. Jordan, and was conceived of as an organization for unaffiliated women to gather for "social and friendly" purposes. The group later expanded its mission to include the promotion of "good fellowship" among campus women, provide a society with honor awards and membership privileges similar to those of sororities, and advance the interests of female students on campus.[1]
Members of the Senior Society were selected from the junior class on the basis of their scholastic record, including grade point average, and leadership skills. The nine founding members of the Senior Society, all from the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts class of 1906, were Anna Waugh, Louise Orth, Cecile Schirmer, Fannie Morris, Juliet Stockbridge (also A.M. 1909), Eleanor Armstrong, Helen Converse, Belle Maclean, and Alice Baker.
In addition to providing scholarships to women, the Senior Society participated in a wide range of campus activities including membership in the Women's League, service projects, career fairs, and sponsorship of dances, teas, and other social events. The group also promoted and encouraged the university's provision of educational resources for women including women's rest rooms, residence halls, and a women's gymnasium.
_____________________________
[1] Margaret Phalan, "Senior Society Founded in 1906 to Promote 'Good Friendship,'" Michigan Daily, March 9, 1933.
The Senior Society records include minutes, 1916-1927 and 1951-1962, scrapbooks, 1941-1954, 1965-1968, and miscellaneous records and membership information. the records are organized into three series: Organizational Records, Scrapbooks, and Artifacts. Content from the related women's honorary societies Scroll and Wyvern is also present in these records.
Subjects:
Scroll (Society).; Senior Society (University of Michigan).; University of Michigan. Assembly Association.; University of Michigan--Honorary Societies.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Wyvern (Society)
- Organizational Records, 1916-1968
  The Organizational Records series, 1906-1962 (0.3 linear feet), includes minutes from Senior Society meetings, reports of the presidents, and copies of the constitution. The minutes cover the years: 1916-1927, and 1951-1962. A partial membership list covers members from 1906 to 1911. Other membership information is in the minutes and scrapbooks.
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - 1916-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1962 (Box 1)
  - Membership List, 1906-1911 (Box 1)
  - Records, 1951-1957 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series, 1941-1968 (0.4 linear feet) includes four separate scrapbooks containing clippings, invitations, tickets, booklets, songs, and some photographs. The scrapbooks cover 1941-1954 and 1965-1968. The women's honoraries were governed by Assembly, an organization established in 1934 to promote the interests of independent women. Information on Assembly is included in the scrapbooks as are frequent references to related honorary societies including Mortar Board, Wyvern (an honorary for junior women), and Scroll. The scrapbooks covering the 1940s include material relating to women on campus during World War II and wartime activities. The 1956-1957 volume pertains to Scroll. The scrapbook for 1965-1967 contains photographs of the "tapping" and initiation for Wyvern and Senior Society.
  - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1955 (Box 1)
  - Scroll, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Wyvern and Senior Society, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
- Artifacts
  The Artifacts series consists of three "Peter Pan" collars, two of which feature lapels embroidered with the words "Senior Society."
  - Peter Pan Collars, 2 embroidered and 1 unembroidered collars (Box 1)
Related Material
The record group Mortar Board (Society) Pi Sigma Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) contains related content. Researchers may also wish to consult the records of the Women's League (University of Michigan).